<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  #%L
  wcm.io
  %%
  Copyright (C) 2014 wcm.io
  %%
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  #L%
  -->

<document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-changes-plugin/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
  <body>

    <release version="1.9.0" date="not released">
      <action type="add" dev="mceruti">
        MediaHandler: Adds MediaHandler.get(String, Resource) that allows building a media from it's path while still looking up policy/component level settings from the given context resource, like it is done when building a media using MediaHandler.get(Resource). Requires the ComponentPropertyResolverFactory to work and be <![CDATA[<a href="https://wcm.io/wcm/commons/configuration.html">configured</a>]]> properly.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="mrozati" issue="WHAN-33"><![CDATA[
        ResourceMedia: Add support for setting responsive image sizes via HTL. This can be either <code>imageSizes</code> and <code>widthOptions</code> (width + required flag), or <code>pictureSourceMediaFormat</code>, <code>pictureSourceMedia</code> and <code>pictureSourceWidths</code>.
      ]]></action>
      <action type="add" dev="mrozati" issue="WHAN-36">
        ResourceMedia: Support setting custom MediaArgs properties via HTL.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="mrozati" issue="WHAN-37">
        ResourceMedia: Support settting autoCrop mode via HTL.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="mrozati" issue="WHAN-34">
        Support responsive images with multiple media formats and image widths.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="bkalbitz" issue="WHAN-35">
        Avoid duplicated storing for fileReference in File Upload component.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="mceruti">
        mediaPlaceholder.html: Translate the component's jcr:title so the component's translated title is displayed.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.8.2" date="2020-01-30">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Detect media dimensions for original renditions for non-image binaries (from asset metadata).
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Make use of ComponentPropertyResolverFactory to ensure component properties can be read properly on publish instances.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-32">
        DamVideoMediaMarkupBuilder: Use new default video profile names format_aac and format_ogg to support AEM 6.4+.
      </action>
      <action type="remove" dev="sseifert">
        DamVideoMediaMarkupBuilder: Do not generate flash player as fallback.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.8.0" date="2020-01-09">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Switch to AEM 6.3 as minimum version.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        AssetRendition: Use getMetadataValueFromJcr instead of getMetadataValue.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Rendition metadata: Fix generation of rendition metadata for SVG assets in AEM 6.4 and below.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="mrozati">
        MediaNameConstants: Fix typo in wcmio:mediaRepsonsive* node names (still support old node names for backward compatibility).
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.7.2" date="2019-09-10">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-25">
        Granite UI components for file upload and path field: Support "appendPath" parameter.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-27">
        Add i18n translations for Granite UI dialog snippets.
      </action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="1.7.0" date="2019-08-23">
      <action type="add">See <![CDATA[<a href="https://wcm-io.atlassian.net/wiki/x/AYCKS">What's new in Media Handler 1.7.0 and Link Handler 1.3.0</a>]]> for an overview of the new features.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Support TIFF images in media handler (with conversion to JPEG for displaying in browser).
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Support SVG vector images in media handler (without transformation support).
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add Granite UI components: Media Formats Select field and Media Formats data source.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Granite UI fileupload component: Add "Clear transformation" link to clear transformations without clearing the selected image.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add MediaHandler.invalid() method.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add support for image maps produced by AEM image editor.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add Granite UI dialog snippets for media format selection and responsive image settings.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Support resolving media handler-related component properties from content policies and component properties.
        This includes media formats, auto cropping and responsive image settings.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-24">
        Allow to specify "sizes" attribute for picture sources.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        PathField and FileUpload Granite UI components: Support expression language for properties 'mediaFormats', 'mediaFormatsMandatory', 'mediaCropAuto', 'allowUpload'.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Inline Media Resource: Support rotation and auto-cropping.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Media placeholder: Support additional classAppend parameter.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Auto-generated IPE cropping ratios: Provide ratios from all image media formats if no media format defined for a media request.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Rendition metadata: Also create rendition metadata for SVG original rendition, as AEM itself is not storing width/height in the asset metadata for SVG.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Media handler download media format validation: Accept any files as download when no download media format is defined in the project and no media format is given for resolution.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Media format validation from GraniteUI components: Fix encoding problem when asset paths contains special chars.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.6.0" date="2019-07-22">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert"><![CDATA[
        Add workflow process implementation to generate rendition metadata. See <a href="https://wcm-io.atlassian.net/wiki/x/AQDrRw">How-to article</a>.
      ]]></action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Rendition metadata generation: Store timestamp for rendition metadata, and re-generate it only if rendition was updated more recently.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Rendition metadata generation: Do not remove metadata for existing renditions (e.g. if listener events are processed with delays).
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Rendition metadata generation: Synchronize writing asset metadata per asset path to avoid threading conflicts.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.5.2" date="2019-06-06">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-23">
        MediaBuilder: Allow media formats without ratios for picture sources.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.5.0" date="2019-05-20">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Allow to define a mix of mandatory and non-mandatory media formats.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Allow to define mandatory and non-mandatory widths for responsive image handling with image sizes or picture source sets.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Allow media formats without ratio for auto-generated IPE cropping ratios (free-hand cropping).
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Allow responsive image handling based in "imageSizes" also for media formats without ratio.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Prefer original renditions above other renditions when creating virtual renditions on-the-fly.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Allow to set default DAM root path for Granite UI components in Media Handler configuration.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Fix potential NPE in GraniteUI components when current content resource cannot be detected.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.4.0" date="2019-04-05">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add switch in media handler config and media args to include or exclude AEM-generated web renditions in media handling (default: included).
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Create AssetRendition class to get dimensions and other information for asset renditions.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Granite UI components: Allow to remove auto-generated field description by setting it to an empty string.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.3.0" date="2019-03-15">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add responsive image handling support using image sizes and picture sources to media handler and SimpleImageMediaMarkupBuilder.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Deprecate non-HTML standard way of responsive image handling using ResponsiveMediaFormatsBuilder and ResponsiveImageMediaMarkupBuilder.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Use wcm.io WCM Granite UI Extension path fields.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Do not apply auto-cropping when manual cropping parameters are present, that lead to a mismatch with the requested media format.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.2.0" date="2019-02-22">
      <action type="add">See <![CDATA[<a href="https://wcm-io.atlassian.net/wiki/x/AYCHOQ">What's new in wcm.io Media Handler 1.2</a>]]> for an overview of this release.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add support for (optional) auto-cropping of DAM assets when no matching rendition exists.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Automatic customization of image in-place edititing crop ratios to ratios from configured media formats.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add Media Handler-aware File Upload and Path Field Granite UI widgets.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add Media Handler-aware placeholder HTL template.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add support for component properties for media formats and auto cropping.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaHandler: Fallback to first media source defined if no matching media source is found.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaFormat: Allow to specify ratio with/height as double, and try to guess nice humban-readable ratio display string.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Switch to AEM 6.2 as minimum version.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Avoid NPE when cropping an asset without a web rendition.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.1.0" date="2019-01-29">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add support for image rotation.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Allow to configure "Adobe standard" property/node names for media reference, cropping, rotation, alt. text and inline media node name via MediaHandlerConfig.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        ResourceMedia: Add optional parameters for refProperty, cropProperty and rotationProperty.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add Rendition.getRatio() method.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Use original rendition for generating the cropped images instead of the web rendition.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Deprecate flash rendition support.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        DamMediaSource: If a "media" drop target already exists make use of it instead off adding a new one which breaks in-place edit mode.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        ResourceMedia: Add css class using MediaBuilder instead of adding it directly to the DOM element.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.10" date="2018-08-27">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Add Jetbrains NotNull/Nullable annotations to API.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.8" date="2018-03-14">
      <action type="update" dev="amuthmann">
        Add AssetRenditionContentDispositionFilter to apply 'Dam Safe Binary' content disposition filter logic also to asset rendition's paths.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Use deep URL to reference 'original' rendition instead of asset URL (revert change from release 1.0.6).
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.6" date="2018-02-22">
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Use asset URL instead of reference to rendition for 'original' rendition.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.4" date="2017-09-12">
      <action type="update" dev="mrozati" issue="WHAN-21">
        MediaBuilder: can set MediaArgs "includeThumbnailAssets", "dragDropSupport" and "property".
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.2" date="2017-08-29">
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-20">
        DefaultRenditionHandler: Fix issue with width/height calculation.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.0" date="2017-04-04">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Switch to AEM 6.1 and Java 8 as minimum versions.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Switched SPI to OSGi services based on wcm.io Sling Commons Context-Aware Services MediaHandlerConfig, MediaFormatProvider.
        Use SPI abstract class instead of interface + abstract helper implementation for MediaHandlerConfig, MediaFormatProvider, MediaSource.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaHandlerConfig: Remove method "getDownloadMediaFormats()" - downloadable media formats are now detected by setting the "donload" flag on the media format definitions.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaFormat: Remove application id, add new flag "download" to mark media formats as download formats which can be linked upon.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaArgs/MediaBuilder: Rename "forceDownload" to "contentDispositionAttachment", add new "download" option.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.10.4" date="2017-03-23">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Make dependencies to wcm.io Config provided.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.10.2" date="2016-04-29">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Relax package version dependency for com.day.cq.commons to support AEM60, AEM61 and AEM62.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.10.0" date="2016-02-16">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add ResourceMedia sling model for UI views.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="bdang" issue="WHAN-14">
        Make the extensions array of an existing MediaFormat unmodifiable.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        Set AEM API and OSGi dependencies to provided scope.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        MediaArgs: interpret empty array for varargs parameter as null array.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert">
        MediaHandler: Introduce new INVALID_MEDIA_FORMAT media invalid reason which is returned when invalid media format names are given.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.9.0" date="2015-09-09">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert" issue="WHAN-13">
        Optional included AEM-generated asset thumbnails for media handling.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.8.0" date="2015-08-21">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Add getMimeType() method to rendition interface.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.7.2" date="2015-04-23">
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Allow MediaHandler to be used outside a Page context (e.g. adapting from a DAM asset resource).
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert">
        Do not return rendition file size for virtual renditions (it's wrong to return the DAM rendition size, and too costly to calculate the real size).
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.7.0" date="2015-04-17">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert" issue="WCMIO-68">
        Add Responsive Image Media Markup Builder.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.6.2" date="2015-01-30">
      <action type="fix" dev="sseifert" issue="WCMIO-40">
        Avoid NPE if original rendition is not present.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="isechyn" issue="WCMIO-44">
        CropRenditionHandler should consider the biggest web enabled rendition
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.6.0" date="2015-01-12">
      <action type="update" dev="sseifert" issue="WCMIO-39">
        Drop Target Area definition in DamMediaSource should provide more control for activation and deactivation on the component level.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="isechyn" issue="WCMIO-40">
        CropRenditionHandler should prefer the virtual crop rendition but still consider other renditions for media resolving.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.5.0" date="2014-11-05">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Initial release.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.0" date="2014-10-02">
      <action type="add" dev="sseifert">
        Preliminary release.
      </action>
    </release>

  </body>
</document>
